Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov.
So today's דף daf is the last דף daf of חגיגה. Chagigah.
We pick up in the middle of כו עמוד ב kaf-vav amud-bet
and we'll be finishing it at the end to כז עמוד א.
kaf-zayin amud-alef. בוקר
טוב, boker tov, בוקר טוב boker tov everyone. גמר חתימה טובה G'mar
chatima tova I should also say. So we pick up the line
תנא: Tanna: נאמנים על כלי חרס... ne'emanim al klei cheres... of ירושלים
נאמנים על הקודש. Yerushalayim ne'emanim al ha-kodesh.
So it is, where is it?
It's the, it's about 15, four lines before the last משנה. Mishnah.
No, the second to last. No, like there's three משניות. Mishnayos. Yeah,
it's very confusing. They're about 15 lines down in the wide lines,
okay? The word תנא Tanna appears at the end of the line
right after two dots.
Okay. So this is talking about special circumstances in which we believe
people. So we've already found out that we believe קודש kodesh at
all times, at least in יהודה. Yehuda. We believe people about תרומה
trumah at the time of the olive press and about the vessels
of תרומה trumah relating to תרומה trumah even 70 days at the
time of the pressing of the olives and the grapes, the vessels
even 70 days before.
And then about כלי חרס, klei cheres, we believe them even in
the within, you know, 15 מיל mil from מודיעין ולפנים Modi'in velifnim
around ירושלים. Yerushalayim. We believe people who are coming and returning objects:
גנבים, gannavim, tax collectors, what they did and didn't touch, a lot
of, lot of cases where we're believing people.
And now we get to the line which says, and in ירושלים
נאמנים על הקודש. Yerushalayim ne'emanim al ha-kodesh. In ירושלים Yerushalayim they're always
believed related to קודש, kodesh, which is similar to what we said
except here saying ירושלים Yerushalayim before we said יהודה, Yehuda, so that's
a little strange why it seems to be more limited and we'll
see that in the גמרא. Gemara. And on the רגל, regel, everybody
is believed even on תרומה trumah even though it's not the time
of the pressing of the, of the olives and the grapes. So
let's take a look at that. תנא: Tanna: ובירושלים נאמנים על הקודש.
uv'Yerushalayim ne'emanim al ha-kodesh. תנא: Tanna: נאמנים על כלי חרס גסים לקודש.
ne'emanim al klei cheres gassim lekodesh. So as opposed to within 15
מיל mil of ירושלים Yerushalayim from מודיעין ולפנים Modi'in velifnim they're believed
on the small and the thin vessels or maybe not small we
discussed before but at least you know like the non-major vessels, the
thin ones, the more regularly used ones, they're believed even from 15
מיל mil in. In ירושלים Yerushalayim proper they're believed on all vessels
that are made, all כלי חרס klei cheres that are made for
the purpose
of
קודש. kodesh. וכל כך למה? ve-chol kach lama? שאין עושין כבשונות בירושלים.
she'ein osin kivshonot b'Yerushalayim. Since you don't make kilns in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
so therefore there's a greater need, so you have to go ahead
and buy it, you know, in the industrial area like in the
outskirts of ירושלים Yerushalayim and so on as we said before and
therefore there's a greater need to believe people and again here therefore
policy dictates that we'll have greater believability. Not exactly clear what the
difference is between the small the thin ones which are believed outside
ירושלים Yerushalayim and the big ones only in ירושלים Yerushalayim but it
seems at least a basic difference is that the small ones are
a much more like regular use, and everybody uses them and you
know they're used much more commonly, there's a much higher demand, a
much greater amount of them and therefore there has to be and
therefore you believe even to a greater extent even outside ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
whereas these there's less of a demand so therefore only in ירושלים
Yerushalayim proper. ובשעת הרגל אף על התרומה. uv'sha'as ha-regel af al ha-trumah.
And now we're getting to what's going to be the emphasis of
the end of this משנה, mishnah, of the end of the פרק,
perek, and really what what the whole פרק perek was about, is
that at the time of the רגל regel all of these distinctions
fall away and everybody is believed even on תרומה. trumah. מנא הני
מילי? mina hanei milei? Now as opposed to saying you know if
you would have sort of said similar maybe to as points said
before, well maybe it's to give כוהנים kohanim an opportunity to receive
תרומה. trumah. The same way we believe people in particular at the
time of the at the pressing of the olives and of the
grapes, and רש"י Rashi said because you know that's the major time
when תרומה trumah when the olive oil and the wine is being
produced and therefore the major time that תרומה trumah is being distributed
and you don't want the חברים chaveirim to be excluded from receiving
תרומה, trumah, then you might have said well you know maybe sometimes
people will wait till עלייה לרגל aliyah l'regel to like distribute תרומה
trumah and everybody's going to be around, you could have given maybe
some other type of a policy like that but here we find
that the policy in place actually is much less about receiving תרומה
trumah and what you're getting and much more about creating a sense
of unity amongst בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So let's take a look.
מנא הני מילי? mina hanei milei? אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי: Amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi: דאמר קרא: d'amar kra: ויאסף כל איש ישראל
אל העיר כאיש אחד חברים. vaye'asef kol ish Yisrael el ha-ir k'ish
echad chaveirim. Everybody gathered to the city as one man, as one
person,
as חברים. chaveirim. So it's a little cute little play on words:
הכתוב עשאן כולן חברים. ha-kasuv asam kulan chaveirim. So you see, the
תורה Torah called them all חברים, chaveirim, because they were all so
they were all at the status of a חבר. chaver. Well, what
basically the point being that at the time of עלייה לרגל aliyah
l'regel where the whole idea...
What? I believe it was רגל, regel, yes. So, the point is
though that you see that the whole point of עליה לרגל, Aliyah
l'Regel, right, is that everybody comes up. I mean, although it is
interesting, by the way, to think of the beginning of the מסכת,
masechet, it's worth remembering that in the beginning of the מסכת masechet
we learned about all the people that were exempt from the רגל,
regel, from עליה לרגל, Aliyah l'Regel, right? Any non-males, any people with
various types of other issues. So in a way that that was
creating essentially certain types of divisions. At least who had to come,
not necessarily was allowed to, but who had to. At the same
time, the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, and I'll remind you, said that while those
exemptions applied to who was obligated to bring a קרבן, korban, they
did not apply to the idea of being עולה לרגל. oleh l'regel.
The ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually understood that everybody was obligated to be עולה
לרגל, oleh l'regel, men and women regardless, and they learned it from
הקהל. Hakhel. Because by הקהל Hakhel it says, you know, it says
that when you do הקהל, Hakhel, it says you do it after
חג הסוכות, Chag haSukkot, בעלות כל ישראל לראות את פני, b'alot kol
Yisrael lera'ot et p'nei, right, when all of ישראל Yisrael comes up
in order to appear before God. It says הקהל את העם האנשים
והנשים והטף. Hakhel et ha'am, ha'anashim veha'nashim vehataf. So there it says
that everybody has come up, and then it says gather everyone, men,
women, and children. So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi learns from there that the
actual עליה לרגל Aliyah l'Regel is done by everybody. No distinctions, men,
women, children, no distinctions at all. The בבלי Bavli never actually said
that in the opening תוספות tosafot in the מסכת masechet and proved
from various places in the בבלי Bavli that the בבלי Bavli would
not agree with that. And nevertheless,
and wait, I should also mention one other interesting irony. You might
remember that the other persons that were excluded from עליה לרגל Aliyah
l'Regel according to the בבלי Bavli were people that were extremely smelly.
Remember that? People that had very smelly occupations because they could not
come up, tanners, together with the rest of ישראל. Yisrael. Nobody would
want to go up with them. People wouldn't want them as part
of the group. So in a way, the beginning of the מסכת
masechet opens up with a sense of, well, you gotta get people
together, but only certain people, and other people can't be part of
that group, right? Other people wouldn't want them to be a part
of you. And the end of the מסכת masechet ends by saying
that at the time of עליה לרגל Aliyah l'Regel
we're doing everything we can to create a sense of unity. And
in order to, even the normal stratifications of society, of the עמי
הארץ amei ha'aretz and the חברים chaverim and all of that, we
are completely dealing away with with the רגל. regel. Because just imagine
if all of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael is there and everybody is
sort of guarded and protecting themselves from everybody else and don't touch
my thing and I don't know who you are and I don't
know if you're a חבר chaver or an עם הארץ am ha'aretz
and so on. And all of a sudden, right, especially like it's
one thing in your normal when you're at home and you know
who's who. Then at least you can naturally navigate. Here there's thousands
of people, hundreds of thousands of people, you'd have to avoid everyone.
So דוקא davka what they do at this time is, you know,
as contrasted from the distinctions at the beginning of the מסכת, masechet,
here we completely eradicate the distinctions to create this sense of unity.
Yes, you're going to tell me the context wasn't רגל. regel.
What? There'd be a beautiful irony. The context is ל"ג בעומר. Lag
b'Omer. Oh, really? Okay, that's it.
רבי
עקיבא,
Rabbi
Akiva,
okay, that's very nice.
So that's not the right context. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi I think has
another פסוק pasuk which is ירושלים עיר שחברה לה יחדו. Yerushalayim ir
shechubra lah yachdav. העיר שכלו Ha'ir shekulu that everybody is נעשו חברים.
na'aseh chaverim. So that has more to do with the idea of
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, in ירושלים Yerushalayim everybody's friends. Yes.
I want to ask a general question about רש"י Rashi on the
specific רש"י Rashi here.
Yes, שאין עושים כבשנות בירושלים. she'ein osim kivshonot b'Yerushalayim. See that רש"י?
Rashi? לא לדקים ולא לגסים, lo l'dakim v'lo l'gasim, right? Then he
goes, and this is very typical,
ומיהו בדקים הוצרך לאנשי ירושלים u'mihu b'dakim hutzrach l'anshei Yerushalayim להחפיץ ולהחפיץ
l'hachpich v'hachpich etc. How does he know that?
Well, he doesn't know it.
In other words, can I assume that that's the מסורה mesorah he
got from
his teacher or is it סברא? svara? He's trying to explain, I
mean, sometimes he says כך שמעתי kach shamati or whatever, but he's
just trying to reconcile a problem. Like if there's this need to
believe people about כלי חרס, k'lei cheres, why is there a difference
between big ones and small ones in ירושלים Yerushalayim and outside of
ירושלים? Yerushalayim?
So he's speculating, he's giving a reason. So often times basically it's
סברא svara that we're relying on the ראשון. Rishon. Yeah. Yeah.
I
mean I don't know, you don't have any general sense how much
of רש"י Rashi he's taking from מסורה mesorah and how much he's
thinking out himself. I don't think there's any way of
assuming
which is which here.
So you see in the point of ירושלמי Yerushalmi is it's only
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but according to בבלי Bavli it's as long as
they go together?
You know, that's an interesting question because the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, the בבלי
Bavli does mention שעת הרגל, shas ha'regel,
but the, you know, I think it's an interesting question in the
משנה, Mishnah, whether you read it ובירושלים, u'v'Yerushalayim, you know, does בשעת
הרגל b'shas ha'regel go on ירושלים? Yerushalayim? The sense always is that
we're talking within ירושלים, Yerushalayim, not like for the few people that
were left behind, you know,
because the whole point is everybody is gathering together and everybody's gathering
together in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But it's an interesting point, right, because what
about people who wouldn't go לרגל?
l'regel? Yeah, I understand. I don't think so. It's a good point,
right? I've always assumed it's ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it's partly how you read
that משנה, Mishnah, but that's what I'm taking for, that's what I'm
assuming. Okay, now let's take a look. הפותח את חביתו והמתיך בעיסתו,
Hapotayach et chavito v'hamatich b'isato, so now you're going to have interesting
questions because if you believe בשעת הרגל, b'shas ha'regel, what happens after
the רגל? regel? There you are, your store owner in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
you open up your store, right? You're not going to stand guard
and make sure, but that's part of the whole reason for this
policy, right, at any... anybody can come in and can touch things,
and maybe they want to taste a little bit of the wine,
so they take a little cup and they do a little wine
tasting, and you know whatever and they wind up touching things, so
fine during the רגל regel you don't have to be concerned who's
who and everybody can trust it and everybody can assume it's טהור
tahor and all of that. Now what happens after the רגל regel
and you have a half open barrel of wine? What do you
have to assume? Right remember now that might seem absurd that the
status would change, but you might remember before, right the same guy
who was selling the pictures, you know when he's within מודיעין Modi'in
he's believed and when he's outside of מודיעין Modi'in the same guy
in the same pictures he's not believed.
Close them up but you open them up again next year.
Well I guess you could do that, but you also had a
similar thing exactly about the stuff about the people during the time
of the pressing of the wine. If you can deliver it during
the time of the pressing of the wine you're believed, if you
come late you're not believed, right? So maybe here the status will
change. On the other hand you know there's already a ruling about
this particular barrel, so let's take a look. הפותח את חביתו ומתחיל
בעיסתו, Hapote'ach es chavito umatchil be'isaso, you opened up your barrel ומתחיל
בעיסתו, umatchil be'isaso, you began making bread, אגב הרגל, agav haregel, you
know whatever you should have started I guess distributing dough from the
bread during the רגל. regel. רבי יהודה אומר יגמור, Rabbi Yehuda omer
yigmor, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says even after the רגל regel you
can finish it, you can assume it remains טהור, tahor, because we
won't, you know you won't want to start selling it during the
רגל regel if it's going to have to be טמא tamei after
the רגל. regel. וחכמים אומרים לא יגמור, V'chachamim omrim lo yigmor, and
the וחכמים v'Chachamim say you cannot. So the גמרא Gemara says you
know it changes status. יתיב רב אמי ורב יצחק נפחא אקילעא דרב
יצחק נפחא. Yasiv Rav Ami v'Rav Yitzchak Nafcha akila d'Rav Yitzchak Nafcha.
So רב אמי Rav Ami and רב יצחק נפחא Rav Yitzchak Nafcha
were sitting on like the you know the porch of רב יצחק
נפחא. Rav Yitzchak Nafcha. פתח חד ואמר, Patach chad v'amar,
one of them opened up and said מהו שיניחנה לרגל אחר, Ma'u
sheyanichena l'regel acher, you see that Rabbi Dov they were taking this
cue from you. All right so according to the חכמים Chachamim that
לא יגמור, lo yigmor, can you do like what you did with
the wine that was pressed during שעת הגיתות sha'as hagitos and just
wait until the next רגל? regel?
By the way this is for תרומה? terumah?
Yeah I mean that's why we'd be most concerned, I mean it
could be for people that eat their חולין בטהרת התרומה, chullin b'taharas
hatruma, but basically you know the most concern is with תרומה. terumah.
Okay
but if you're selling a barrel of wine presumably you're not selling
תרומה, terumah, so it applies to חולין chullin as well, okay it
applies to everything. So let's take a look.
So אמר ליה אידך amar lei idach ידא הכל ממשמשין בה yada
hakol memash'shin bah ואת אמרת יניחנה לרגל אחר? v'at amrat yanichena l'regel
acher? So everybody is handling it and you're saying wait till the
next רגל? regel? Meaning look give a give me a break once
it's no longer the רגל regel we have to
revert to what we know is our real concerns which is it
probably is טמא. tamei. So even if we were willing to suspend
that during the רגל regel we cannot suspend it after the רגל,
regel, okay of course but so what but during the רגל regel
you do suspend it. So אמר ליה amar lei אטו עד האידנא
לאו ידא הכל ממשמשין בה? atu ad idna lav yada hakol memash'shin
bah? He says I don't get it, so what? During the רגל
regel also everybody is handling it but you're willing to suspend those
concerns so suspend it when the next רגל regel runs around. אמר
ליה amar lei הכי השתא, hachi hashta, says what are you talking
about? בשלמא עד האידנא טומאת עם הארץ ברגל רחמנא טהרה. Bishlama ad
idna tumas am ha'aretz b'regel rachmana tahara. The טומאה tumah of an
עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, now notice the phrase the רחמנא, Rachmana, the
Torah was מטהר metaher it, right because it quotes a פסוק pasuk
ויאסף כל איש ישראל v'ye'esof kol ish Yisrael which isn't in the
Torah and as was pointed out is talking about פילגש בגבעה Pilegesh
b'Givah isn't directly relevant but nevertheless and all these
חומרות chumras are rabbinic חומרות, chumras, but nevertheless maybe because it was
felt so deeply problematic you know that ממש mammesh you believe everybody
about everything or whatever, you know invoking the authority of the Torah,
the Torah made it טהור, tahor, let's
finish, רחמנא Rachmana made it טהור. tahor. So that okay there we
understand. אלא השתא טמיא היא, Ela hashta tmeia hi, but once the
רגל regel is over it gets a status of being טמא. tamei.
During the רגל regel it never got that status yet, it was
considered טהור, tahor, but as soon as that passes it becomes טמא.
tamei. So
נימא neima so therefore there's no way it can go from טמא
tamei to being back to being טהור. tahor. It's a way that
that state can be suspended or can be prevented, but once that
state takes effect it's going to remain in that state. What's interesting
about this is you know which okay you sort of understand the
point being made that once we acknowledge the problem we can no
longer ignore it. Once we acknowledge עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz touched it
they were probably טמא, tamei, we have to treat it as טמא,
tamei, can't go ahead and ignore that. The difference presumably the difference
like before like the issue about at the time of the pressing
of the grapes of the olives and so on was that that
was considered to be a period when people would make an effort
to be מטהר metaher everything. So there at least there was some
type of a fact pattern there was some type of a basis
of an argument we could make why maybe it really is טהור.
tahor. So it would not be so bad to say okay the
period of the pressing passed we can't trust it when the period
comes back we can trust it because at least there's something we
can rely on. Here there's nothing we can rely on. It's not
an assumption that oh everybody is מטהר metaher themselves although you might
want to have said that people מטהר metaher themselves for the רגל,
regel, but for some reason that's not being said and therefore as
long as we sort of suspend that live in like you know
sort of you know what what what what what do they call
that when you're supposed to be friction a state of suspended disbelief.
When we live in a state of suspended disbelief, okay, we're okay,
but as soon as we pull out of that and it's after
the רגל regel we acknowledge that all the עם הארץ am ha'aretz
touched it and there's no reason to think it's טהור, tahor, we
have to treat it טמא, tamei, says there's no reason we can
go back and treat it as טהור tahor again. Okay, so that
is you understand where he's coming from. What is interesting is again
number one the contrast to when we do exactly that like in
the case of the time of the pressings of the of the
oil and of the and of the wine and what's also interesting
is the phrase of רחמנא טיהרא Rachmana tihara which again we have
first time we're introducing treating it as if it's דאורייתא de'oraita although
this is דרבנן derabbanan but I think that's partly because it's so
shocking that we're going to be so lenient that you sort of
invoke the authority of the תורה. Torah. Yes.
You have a situation with חזקה chazaka where you have a certain
set of facts and despite facts an עירוב eruv falls down in
a hurricane and you see it. You'll tell everybody else and you'll
allow them to continue to use the...
No, that's not true. Not true? No, that's not true. That's not
true. I mean there might be reason you don't tell people because
מוטב יהיו שוגגין mutav yiheyu shogegin but that's
that's that's different.
Okay, but what... doesn't everyone have to be in the... it's שבת
רגל Shabbat regel everyone has to go to...
First of all, first of all two things. First of all, you
can bring a קרבן korban without appearing in the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. Second of all, right, the types of טומאה וטהרה tumah ve'taharah
that they're concerned about here, you know, I mean it's interesting, right,
what... Yeah, I mean it is true if you want to appear
in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash you would have to be you'd
have to be טהור. tahor.
So
you can say there's a רוב, rov, רוב rov people are appearing
in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
Yeah, but you know, I mean first of all it's for the
entirety of the רגל, regel, so after you've brought your קרבן korban
like, you know, why to continue to assume that you're being so
careful and scrupulous and so on? And remember that when it comes
to קודש kodesh we believe people more because you don't want to
exclude people from the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So we've always sort
of operated that way, you know. Now again you could say, well
once you're, you know, that's part of the logic here, once you're
accepting them to come into the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you know,
it it is interesting sort of living in different modes. But anyway,
but it just felt that it was very hard to sustain. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, נימא כתנאי, neima ketannai, let's
say it's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא חדא, detanya chada, one
one ברייתא beraita says, יניחנה לרגל אחר, yanichennah leregel acher, and תניא
אידך, vethanya idach, לא יניחנה לרגל אחר. lo yanichennah leregel acher. So
you see there's exactly this debate, מאי לאו תנאי, mai lav tannai,
you see it's a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, תנאים Tannaim whether you
can leave it to the next רגל. regel. לא, lo, the גמרא
Gemara says הך דתני יניחנה, hach detani yanichennah, leave it to the
next רגל, regel, רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehudah. That's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah
who says that you can keep finish it. Of course the question
is why do you have to leave it? We'll get to that.
והך דתני לא יניחנה, vehach detani lo yanichennah, don't leave it, רבנן.
Rabbanan. That's the rabbis who say that what it's no good after
the רגל regel and remains no good. גמרא Gemara says ותסברא, vethisbara,
does that really make sense? הא רבי יהודה יגמור קאמר. ha Rabbi
Yehudah yigmor ka'amar. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah doesn't need you to leave
it till the next רגל, regel, he says you can finish it
immediately, you can keep on eating it afterwards. So so אלא הך
דתני ela hach detani fine, we'll reverse it. הך דתני לא יניחנה,
hach detani lo yanichennah, when it says don't leave it to the
next רגל, regel, רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehudah. That's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah
and we're going to say what that means is you don't have
to leave it to the next רגל. regel. הך דתני יניחנה, hach
detani yanichennah, when it says leave it to the next רגל, regel,
רבנן. Rabbanan. It's the rabbis. ומאי לא יניחנה, umai lo yanichennah, what
does it mean don't leave it? שאין צריך להניח, she'ein tzarich lehaniach,
that you don't have to leave it to the next רגל regel
according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehudah, you can finish it right away.
But either way what we see is there is one opinion that
says יניחנה, yanichennah, you can leave it to the next רגל, regel,
which would make it like the wine and the oil that you
pressed בשעת הגיתות, bish'at haggitot, and there's a question what the other
opinion means. But at the simple sense it does seem that this
is exactly a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, how much does this parallel
what we've seen by the issue of the שעת הגיתות. sha'at haggitot.
Okay, so that's in terms of trusting every בעל בית ba'al bayit
about תרומה. terumah. My question is a good question that in general
they're trusted to bring קרבנות korbanot and קודש kodesh and so on,
but as we've known there's we're always more מחמיר machmir in terms
of תרומה terumah and here during the time of the רגל regel
we are not. משעבר הרגל, mishe'avar haregel, so that's in terms of
food that they've handled. But now we're going to take take
sort of look at something even more shocking, which is their possible
touching of the כלים keilim of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Let's
take a look. משעבר הרגל, mishe'avar haregel, once the רגל regel is
over, מעבירין על טהרת עזרה, ma'avirin al taharat azarah, you take out
all the vessels of the from the עזרה, azarah, from the temple
courtyard and you immerse them.
עבר הרגל ביום ששי, avar haregel beyom shishi, now if the if
the רגל regel was over on a Friday, לא מעבירין מפני כבוד
השבת, lo ma'avirin mipnei kevod haShabbat, you would not do it because
of שבת Shabbat because you know שבת Shabbat is coming and you're
going to now do a whole major process of immersing all the
vessels and you're not giving anybody כהנים kohanim the time to go
get ready for שבת Shabbat and everything is all very rushed. רבי
יהודה אומר אף לא ביום חמישי, Rabbi Yehudah omer af lo beyom
chamishi, even if it even if the רגל regel was over on
Thursday you wouldn't do it, שאין כהנים פנויים, she'ein kohanim penuyim, that
even starting Thursday people are busy, you know, and and you're not
giving them time to prepare for שבת. Shabbat. Now now not only
that if you look at רש"י Rashi says another reason why they
specifically don't have time, he says לפי שאין הכהנים פנויים במוצאי יום
טוב להטבילה, lefi she'ein hakohanim penuyim bemotza'ei Yom Tov le'hatbilah, they don't
have time to to immerse them on Thursday, שתרודים להוציא הדשן שעל
התפוח שבאמצע מזבח שקיבצו שם כל ימות הרגל כל דשן של מערכה.
shetirudim lehotzi hadeshen
she'al hatapuach shebe'emtza mizbe'ach shekibetzu sham kol yemot haregel kol deshen shel
ma'arachah. So you know they've bringing all these sacrifices the entire רגל,
regel, you're getting a huge mound of ashes, so a major thing
they had to do מוצאי רגל motza'ei regel was take out all
the ashes. So that's their major activity מוצאי הרגל, motza'ei haregel, that's
going to take up a lot of Thursday. So you can't and
then by Friday already you have to got ready for שבת. Shabbat.
So in that case he would wait until the next week.
So there is that in
the גמרא Gemara or is that רש"י? Rashi? Oh, you're right. רש"י
Rashi is just thank you. You're right. Next line in the גמרא:
Gemara: תנא שאין הכהנים פנויים להוציא בדשן. Tana she-ein hakohanim pnu’im le-hotzi
ba-deshen. Right, thank you very much.
So long, Sigiv, thank you. Okay, I forgot that. It's been two
days since I learned this גמרא. Gemara. Okay, anyway, so right, so
there you go. But what's fascinating here is two things: one is
the striking idea that we assume the כלים keilim in the עזרה
azara became טמא, tamei, which we're going to talk about how they
touched them and we're going to talk talk about that in a
minute, but the other thing is if we're assuming that they became
טמא, tamei, we're not then a) during the רגל regel we're not
worrying about it or you know or concerned but not concerned during
the רגל, regel, we're suspending that concern. So during the רגל regel
we're not worried about that, but even after the רגל, regel, if
it's going to be too rushed because it's Friday or maybe even
Thursday, we're going to continue to suspend those concerns for two to
three more days, right, for Thursday, Friday and שבת, Shabbos, when we'll
only start bringing them to the מקוה mikvah on Sunday. So during
the רגל, regel, there's a possibility apparently that an עם הארץ am
ha'aretz touched the כלים keilim in the בית המקדש. beis hamikdash. How
that happened we'll see in a minute. But we're going to suspend
that concern during the רגל regel and we're going to continue to
suspend it maybe even in one or two or three days more
until we get a chance to immerse the vessels. But now we're
going to really have to look at this fascinating issue about how
was it an עם הארץ am ha'aretz might have touched the כלים
keilim in the בית המקדש. beis hamikdash. Yes, very good.
Did you say that it says specifically in the מרדכי Mordechai that
it took night for the vessels to be טמא? tamei? Is it
like that רש"י Rashi or was it somewhere?
I don't know. Okay, כיצד Keitzad anyway we did it here. כיצד
מעבירין על טהרת עזרה. Keitzad ma'avirin al taharas azara. How would what
would this mean that we would remove the כלים keilim to immerse
them? Okay, מטבילין את הכלים שהיו במקדש, matbilin es hakeilim shehayu bamikdash,
you would immerse the vessels that were in the בית המקדש. beis
hamikdash. ואומרים להן ve'omerim lahen and you would say to them now
not when you're immersing it this is during the רגל regel you
would say to the people הזהרו שלא תגעו בשולחן. hizaheru shelo tigu
bashulchan.
Be careful not to touch the שולחן. shulchan. Now this is crazy,
who are you telling to be careful not to touch the שולחן?
shulchan? The שולחן's shulchan not only in the עזרה, azara, right, the
שולחן's shulchan in the in the היכל, heichal, right? So here you
got here you have your בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, here's your אולם,
ulam,
right,
right, yep,
right, I'm just trying to get my directions
right.
So here's your מנורה, menorah, here's your שולחן, shulchan, right, here's your
קודש הקודשים, kodesh hakodashim, right I just have that, okay,
right, here's the מזבח mizbeiach fine. Okay anyway and here's this. Now
where were ישראל Yisroel normally allowed? ישראל Yisroel were normally allowed in
about eleven אמות amos here right of the עזרה azara these were
the gates of the עזרה azara that was שער ניקנור. shaar nikanor.
Now this rest this this was the עזרת כהנים ezras kohanim right
where only כהנים kohanim generally could go and then in here right
nobody could go unless they had to. There was only people that
would go in here would be the person the כהן גדול kohen
gadol and then the ones that were arranging the bread of the
שולחן shulchan or lighting the מנורה menorah right so who the heck
is touching that? So maybe you could say it's like a כהן
עם הארץ. kohen am ha'aretz. But you know there's not too many
people that get to go in here okay two or three maybe
right on a שבת Shabbos they switch the bread so you have
a few a daily they do the מנורה menorah what we're getting
there Michael don't ruin the surprise okay. But anyway so you only
have כהנים kohanim and maybe you have I mean how many כהנים
kohanim go in here you know you burn the קטורת ketores light
the מנורה menorah like one or two a day okay who is
touching you're going to let a כהן עם הארץ kohen am ha'aretz
go in there who is touching the שולחן shulchan why is it?
What do you do for the לויים? Levi'im? It's to the west
of the ניקנור? Nikanor? Yeah on the other side?
No it's over here? There ah okay anyway alright
so so that's takes so the גמרא Gemara says like this
so שלא תגעו בשולחן shelo tigu bashulchan don't touch the שולחן shulchan
and we're going to see the reason that they were so concerned
about the שולחן shulchan is because they could immerse all the other
vessels but they couldn't immerse the שולחן shulchan because the שולחן shulchan
says לחם פנים לפני תמיד lechem panim lefanai tamid that it always
has to be in front so of God so you cannot move
it so that's the one vessel they couldn't immerse. כל הכלים שהיו
במקדש יש להם שניים ושלישים Kol hakeilim shehayu bamikdash yesh lahem sheniyim
ushlishim all the vessels in the מקדש mikdash had you know שניים
ושלישים sheniyim ushlishim seconds and thirds had replacements שאם נטמאו הראשונים יביאו
שניים תחתיהם she-imtameu harishonim yavi'u sheniyim tachteihem that if some became טמא
tamei they would just use the
backup except for the well we'll see the שולחן. shulchan. כל הכלים
שהיו במקדש טעונים טבילה Kol hakeilim shehayu bamikdash te'unim tevila all the
vessels if they became טמא tamei had to be immersed חוץ ממזבח
הזהב וממזבח הנחושת chutz mimizbeiach hazahav umimizbeiach hanechoshet except for the gold
altar and the copper altar the gold was inside the copper was
outside מפני שהן כקרקע mipnei shehein kekarka because they are considered like
they're attached to the ground and therefore they do not become טמא
tamei דברי רבי אליעזר divrei Rabbi Eliezer that's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says. וחכמים אומרים מפני שהן מצופין Vachachamim omrim mipnei shehein metzupin
because they are because they are
coated in metal which is bizarre because that should make them something
that's coated in metal metal is more susceptible to becoming טמא tamei
so it's not clear what the חכמים chachamim are saying we'll see
in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
תנא Tana so it taught in a beraisa הזהרו שלא תגעו בשולחן
ובמנורה hizaheru shelo tigu bashulchan u-vimenora they said not just be careful
not to touch the שולחן shulchan they also said don't touch the
מנורה menorah presumably the מנורה menorah was something that
you... Apparently according to our תנא Tana you could be טובל Tovel
the מנורה. Menorah. So the גמרא Gemara says שלחן כתיב ביה תמיד.
Shulchan ksiv bei tamid. שלחן Shulchan it says לחם פנים לפני תמיד.
Lechem Panim lefanai tamid. So therefore the שלחן Shulchan you could not
move and that was the
issue. But מנורה Menorah לא כתיב בה תמיד. lo ksiv ba tamid.
Now רש"י Rashi says it does say תמיד. tamid. It says by
the מנורה Menorah it says להעלות נר תמיד, le'ahlos ner tamid, but
that's only during nighttime. So there's no תמיד tamid during the day.
The מנורה Menorah only has to be burning during the night. So
therefore,
if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, כלומר תמידים
אמורים במנורה לא תמיד יומם ולילה קאמר אלא תמיד מלילה ללילה
כתמיד האמור בעולת תמיד בחביתי כהן גדול אבל ביום לא היה דולק
מערב עד בוקר כתיב.
klomar temidim amurim bemenorah lo tamid yomam v'layla ka'amar ela tamid milayla
l'layla ketamid ha'amur be'olas tamid bechavitai kohen gadol aval beyom lo
haya dolek me'erev ad boker ksiv. Okay so therefore since the מנורה
Menorah was only the תמיד tamid of the מנורה Menorah was at
night, not in the day, but the תמיד tamid of the שלחן
Shulchan was at all times. So
ואידך, v'idach, so what would the other one say? כתיבן דכתיב את
המנורה נוכח השלחן. ksivan d'ksiv es hamenorah nochach hashulchan. המנורה Hamenorah opposite
השלחן, Hashulchan, כמאן דכתיב בה תמיד דמי. keman d'ksiv ba tamid dami.
So the same way the שלחן Shulchan has to always be there,
the מנורה Menorah has to always be there. ואידך, V'idach, no, ההוא
לקבוע לה מקום הוא דאתא. hahu likvo'a la makom hu d'asya. No,
that's to say that it had a fixed place opposite the שלחן,
Shulchan, but it doesn't say that it has to always be there.
Okay, so basically we have the idea that don't touch the things
that we're not allowed to be טובל. tovel. That certainly is the
שלחן, Shulchan, it might be the מנורה. Menorah. We still don't know
how the heck anybody's getting access to this to touch it, but
you got to be really careful not to touch the things we're
not allowed to be טובל. tovel. וכל כלי עץ העשוי לנחת לא
מיטמא. V'khol kli etz ha'asui lenachas lo mitamei. So now the גמרא
Gemara says, sorry I skipped a line, ותיפוק ליה דכלי עץ העשוי
לנחת הוא וכל כלי עץ העשוי לנחת לא מיטמא. V'teipokei d'kli etz
ha'asui lenachas hu v'khol kli etz ha'asui lenachas lo mitamei. So the
גמרא Gemara says why do you have to be concerned about not
touching the שלחן Shulchan and therefore because you won't be able to
immerse it? The שלחן Shulchan is a wooden vessel, okay, ignoring that
it's covered with gold but it's basically wooden, and therefore any wooden
vessel that is made to remain in its place is like something
attached to the ground, it's not מיטמא. mitamei. Think for example, I
know this isn't wood, but think for example like your refrigerator. Do
you consider your refrigerator a vessel or do you consider it like
part of the apartment, you know? So something that's big and heavy
and when it's full it stays where it is, you know, that
is something that is not considered a vessel, it's considered essentially attached
to the ground, and it's not מיטמא. mitamei. Okay, so therefore the
גמרא Gemara says, isn't that true by the שלחן? Shulchan? And therefore
why do you need to be concerned that it be touched and
you're not allowed to move it etc? It shouldn't become טמא tamei
anyway. וכל כלי עץ העשוי לנחת, V'khol kli etz ha'asui lenachas, any
wooden vessel made for remaining in its place, לא מיטמא, lo mitamei,
it does not become טמא. tamei. מאי טעמא, Mai taama, what's the
reason?
דומיא דשק בעינן. Dumya d'sak be'inan. You need similar to a שק.
sak. Because the תורה Torah speaks about a שק sak being טמא.
tamei. מה שק מיטלטל מלא וריקם, Ma sak mitaltel malei v'reikam, the
same way a שק sak can be carried empty and full, אף
כל מיטלטל מלא וריקם, af kol mitaltel malei v'reikam, only something, at
least wood vessels, that are carried empty and full are things that
can become טמא, tamei, but something that cannot be carried full cannot
become טמא. tamei. So the גמרא Gemara says, and now this can,
now by the way, it's not generally cannot, but more like is
not, is not. The phrase is עשוי לנחת, asui lenachas, made for
the purpose of being in its place. Okay, so a שלחן, Shulchan,
the גמרא Gemara says, look, it's like a little circular. They're saying
don't touch the שלחן Shulchan because we won't be able to move
it to immerse it. So the גמרא Gemara is saying, but because
you're not allowed to move it, that should mean that it can't
become טמא. tamei. You can touch it because because you're not allowed
to move it, right, it is עשוי לנחת. asui lenachas. So it
doesn't just mean something that is not able to be carried full,
but it means something that is not carried. You know, either if
you're not able to, when you fill it up it's too heavy,
or something that maybe you're able to, but in principle you always
leave it exactly in its space. Okay, so that type of thing,
like again, imagine, I don't know, you had a big, what are
those things called, those
armoires, those things they have for like those chests of clothes, you
know, those big standing things, right? So, okay, in theory, maybe you
can carry it, but that thing stays there, it's made to be
in its place and to stay there, right? So that would be
considered לא מיטמא. not mitamei. So that's the שלחן, Shulchan, it's meant
to stay there, it's תמיד. tamid. So exactly because you're not allowed
to move it, it should mean it shouldn't become טמא. tamei. So
let's take a look. הא נמי מיטלטל מלא וריקם הוא, Ha nami
mitaltel malei v'reikam hu, כדריש לקיש. kideresh lakish. Like ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says, דאמר ריש לקיש, d'amar Reish Lakish, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says, מאי דכתיב, mai d'ksiv, what's meant by the verse על השלחן
הטהור, al hashulchan hatahor, that it says you should put the bread
on the טהור שלחן? tahor Shulchan? מכלל שהוא טמא, Miklal shehu tamei,
you gotta love the גמרא Gemara when it does things like that.
It says the טהור שלחן, tahor Shulchan, which means it's טמא. tamei.
So not literally means it's טמא, tamei, it means that it's able
to be טמא. tamei. If it has to tell you that it's
טהור, tahor, so of course a natural way to read it might
be it's always טהור. tahor. No, but the point of having to
say טהור tahor it means that it's possible that it could be
טמא. tamei. How could it be possible it could be טמא? tamei?
I thought it has to remain in its
place? So why is that? כלי עשוי לנחת, Kli asui lenachat, it's
a vessel that's made for being remaining in its place,
and ואינו מקבל טומאה. v'eino mekabel tumah. אלא מלמד, Ela melamed, it
teaches you, שמגביהין אותו, shemagbihin oto, you lift it up, ומראין בו
לעולי רגלים, umarin bo l'olei regalim, and you show it to the
people that are coming up for the רגל, regel, לחם הפנים lechem
hapanim that they can see the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, ואומרים להם,
v'omrim lahem, and you say to them, ראו חיבתכם לפני המקום, reu
chibatchem lifnei hamakom, look at how beloved you are to God. סילוקו
כסידורו, Siluko kesiduro, that the bread remains warm a week later when
it's removed just like when it's put up. דאמר רבי יהושע בן
לוי, D'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, let me read a little, נס
גדול נעשה בלחם הפנים, nes gadol na'asa belechem hapanim, an amazing miracle
was done with the bread. כסידורו כך סילוקו, Kesiduro kach siluko, that
the same way when they put it up it was fresh and
warm, when they removed it it was just as fresh and warm,
שנאמר, shenemar, לשום לחם חם ביום הלקחו, lasum lechem cham beyom hilakcho,
to put warm bread like in the day of its removal. So
just like it was put it was warm, when it was removed
it was warm. Now, so they did lift it up. It was
not that they kept constantly remained it there. Now, where did they
put it? They went to show the people. Where did they show
the people? So here's the thing, okay, there is, all the gates
here are open opposite one another, right? The gate of the שער
ניקנור, Sha'ar Nicanor, the gate of the אולם, Ulam, the gate of
the היכל, Heichal, even the gate of the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim.
I'll remind you to anybody who wants to hear about this, I
gave a שיעור shiur on it at IBT I think at length,
right, that on the רגל regel they would even, you know, push
aside the פרוכת parochet here and push aside all these פרוכות parochot
so that the people could see straight in. Now, how they could
see straight in with the מזבח mizbe'ach there in the way might
have to be a question of exactly where the מזבח mizbe'ach was
situated, there's a מחלוקת machlokes where the מזבח mizbe'ach was situated, okay?
So anyway, it would be possible and they would actually let them
see, I mean, it's completely
like shocking, you know, it's like scandalous, you know, the whole thing
is that it would only be the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur could have entry, and דוקא davka the גמרא
Gemara says that they would make it available at least to see
by the people by pushing all the פרוכות parochot aside. So if
you want to hear more about that, go listen to my שיעור.
shiur. But here, what we're saying is that they would show the
שולחן. shulchan. Now where would they show the שולחן shulchan to the
people? So it's possible all they would do would be to lift
it up and put it down in the center so that at
least people could, at least people could see it through a straight
line. Okay, maybe that's all that's happening, but of course then you
don't still don't understand who's not touching it. Where is there a
concern of people touching? The גמרא Gemara never spells that out. So
it's possible that the only people they're concerned are touching it are
כהנים עם הארץ. Kohanim am ha'aretz. If you look, that's what רש"י
Rashi says. רש"י Rashi says,
ואומרים להם v'omrim lahem on the עמוד א, amud aleph, לכהנים עם
הארץ. le'Kohanim am ha'aretz. So he thinks it's only a problem of
the כהנים. Kohanim. But even according to רש"י, Rashi, like I said,
how many כהנים Kohanim get to go in here each day? You
know, what is it, lighting the מנורה menorah and burning the קטורת?
ketoret? So just make sure those כהנים Kohanim aren't עם הארץ כהנים.
am ha'aretz Kohanim. So okay, maybe they were very you know populist
during the רגל regel and let them go in. It's possible, but
one does wonder if you're trying to show it to the people,
how far do they actually move it? Now I have to admit
that the language does say, right, it says that they were מגביהים
אותו. magbihim oto. So מגביהים magbihim doesn't suggest that they would transport
it very far. But one does wonder would they even actually go
bring it all the way out to actually show the people and
is that possibly how the people could come in contact with it?
Okay, that would be, I mean, I acknowledge that that's not clear
in the גמרא Gemara and the simplest thing in the גמרא Gemara
is that it just means that it moved it a little bit.
Also, since it says לפני תמיד, lifnai tamid, presumably לפני lifnai means
that it has to remain within right within the היכל. Heichal. Presumably
to take it out of
the
היכל Heichal to go to the מקוה, mikvah, but presumably it has
to remain in the היכל. Heichal. So presumably all it means was
that it would be moved center. But there still is a big
question of who are you afraid is touching it.
The same way, what? And how do they see it's warm if
you just move it three feet?
Oh, that's a good point too. You mean how do they see
that it's warm? I don't know, fresh bread you can smell, but
that's a good point, I don't know if you could smell it
that far. That's a good point too, right? Who is looking at
it? So there really is an interesting possibility that they really got
it somehow a lot closer to the people. I will also let
you know by the way that on סוכות, Sukkot, right, and this
is another way in which the חז"ל Chazal gave the people much
more access than you would normally imagine is on סוכות Sukkot they
would do הקפה hakafa with ערבות. aravos. Now again, you could say
that was just the כהנים, Kohanim, but the פשט pshat of the
משנה Mishna is that they would do the הקפה hakafa with the
ערבות, aravos, right, would be כל ישראל. kol Yisrael. And that would
even go into the spot between אולם Ulam and מזבח, mizbe'ach, which
is considered to generally be off limits even to כהנים Kohanim unless
they have to go there. Okay, but if ישראל Yisrael is actually
not just in the עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, but in here and
doing the הקפות hakafot or whatever, you know, you really wonder, it
sounds like the people are getting a lot of close access to
the כלים keilim of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash that they normally
would not have and that's why you would have to do this
טבילה. tevila. So again, what this is showing is not just the
idea of creating a sense of Of אחדות achdus like on the
רגל regel everybody is one, we don't want to create divisions, we're
going to treat everybody as טהור tahor and not just like oh,
we'll consider you טהור. tahor. Even if you're טהור, tahor, you're never
allowed in there, but it's really a very different aspect which gets
back to the beginning of the מסכת, masechet, which is the whole
idea of עליה לרגל aliyah leregel and ראייה, re-iyah, יראה כל זכורך,
ye-ira-eh kol zechurcha, right, את פני אדני השם, es pnei Adonai Hashem,
so the idea of appearing before God, but as we discussed earlier
there, the simple sense of the verse is not just appearing, but
the פשט pshat of the verse is יראה כל זכורך את פני,
ye-ira-eh kol zechurcha es pnei, to see, seeing God. How does one
see God? לא יראני אדם וחי, lo yirani adam vachai, but obviously
people are going up to the רגל, regel, they presumably want some
direct encounter, they just don't want to appear and bring their קרבן,
korban, they're finally getting to see the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash where
God is present, they want some sense of some encounter with God
and what the חכמים Chachamim are doing is that they are actually
allowing, they're pulling aside the curtains, they're bringing the מנורה menorah into
their vision, maybe bringing the מנורה menorah out, they're letting the people
in, they're giving them, the שלחן, Shulchan, excuse me, the שלחן, Shulchan,
they're giving them a much greater, sort of sense of encounter than
normally, you know, logically they should have been afforded. And it will
not come as a surprise that the צדוקים Tzedukim were very much
against all of this, this was very much the חז"ל Chazal and
the פרושים Perushim and a real attempt to make the מקדש Mikdash
accessible to the people, which really ties into the themes that we've
been seeing. You want to say something Charlie?
Yes, okay, also ערב פסח Erev Pesach they're all over the place,
checking the...
Yeah, but there they were presumably within here. Here we really sort
of see a much greater getting them closer in and getting the
things that are inside closer out. Okay, more that, listen to the
שיעור shiur that I put out ערב יום כיפור. Erev Yom Kippur.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: ותיפוק ליה משום ציפוי. v'teipok lei mishum tzipui. Okay, says the
גמרא, Gemara, but maybe it's טמא tamei not because they would lift
it up and move it, maybe it could become טמא tamei in
theory, obviously they would, the whole point is to avoid that, but
maybe it could become טמא tamei in theory because it's coated with
gold.
דתנן, detnan, השלחן והדופקי שנפחתו hashulchan vehadufki shenifchatu or שחיפן בשיש. shechippan
beshayish. If you have a table or a דופקי dufki which is
some type of a also a what does רש"י Rashi say it
is? כסא, kisei, right, some kind of a folding chair, that either
have, you know, have come have broken or that they were covered
let's say in marble. ושיאר בהם מקום הנחת כוסות, veshi-eir bahem mekom
hanachas kossos, marble is does not become טמא, tamei, but there's enough
of a space on it to put some to put some cups,
so some glasses, so טמא. tamei. It's טמא tamei because it's still
functional and that much is still, you know, uncovered uncoated with marble
and still wood and still functional. רבי יהודה אומר מקום הנחת החתיכות.
Rabbi Yehuda omer mekom hanachas hachatichos. It has to have a place
of putting like actually like pieces of meat essentially. Okay, so what
do you see? You see though if you coat it with marble,
it will change its status. If it's completely coated and that's to
make it טהור. tahor. So how much more so if you coat
it with metal will it change its status to make it טמא?
tamei? And metal vessels, even if they're made for staying in a
place, become טמא. tamei. So maybe the reason the שלחן Shulchan can
become טמא tamei is not because it's moved, but because it is
considered to be metal. וכי תימא שאני עצי שיטים דחשיבי ולא בטילי?
vechi teima shani atzei shitim dechashivi velo bateili? Maybe acacia wood, which
is what the שלחן Shulchan was made of, is considered very important
wood and even if coated with gold, it's still considered to be
a wood vessel not a gold vessel. That's a pretty funny idea,
that the wood is more significant than the gold and makes the
gold considered secondary to it. הניחא לריש לקיש דאמר לא שנו אלא
בכלי אכסלגין הבאים ממדינת הים. hanicha le-Reish Lakish de-amar lo shanu ela
bichlei achsalgin haba-im mimedinas hayam. That's good for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
who says that this idea that coating changes the status of the
wood vessel underneath is by a certain type of these the wood
that comes from overseas. אבל בכלי מסמים לא בטילי. aval bichlei mesamim
lo bateili. But with a different type of a wood that's more
important wood and I'll say oak or something, then the coating would
not change its status. שפיר, shappir, that's good, so maybe you could
say that even the gold doesn't change the status of the שלחן
Shulchan and the שלחן Shulchan is still considered a wood a wood
table. אלא לרבי יוחנן דאמר אפילו בכלי מסמים נמי בטילי מאי איכא
למימר?
ella le-Rabbi Yochanan
de-amar
afilu bichlei mesamim nami bateili mai ika lemeimar? But according to רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who says that even with very important wood, it
loses its status based on the covering, so what can if the
coating, what can you say? This wood should be considered a metal
vessel and that's why it's טמא tamei because it's a metal vessel,
not because you move it. That's why it can become
טמא. tamei. וכי תימא כאן בציפוי עומד כאן בציפוי שאינו עומד? vechi
teima kan betzipui omed kan betzipui she-eino omed? Maybe there's a difference
between whether the coating really is like a good solid one or
it is one that, you know, and really sort of stands by
itself or it does not really it's not really supported. רש"י, Rashi,
if you look at רש"י, Rashi, ציפוי שאינו עומד, tzipui she-eino omed,
רש"י Rashi says שאינו מחוזק במסמרים יפה. she-eino mechuzzak be-masmerim yafeh. וצפוי
דמקדש לאו עומד הוא. vetzipui de-Mikdash lav omed hu. So it's two
interesting ideas. Number one, the coating is not like I'll not again,
I don't understand, normally you assume coating it means you actually, you
know, layer it on, so embedding it, right, like it gets embedded
in. Here I imagine it's like a plate that gets hammered on
top like nailed on top like a separate like, you know, plating
that gets nailed on top of it. So if that's the case,
maybe if it's not well layered on top and it could easily
come off, it doesn't change its status. Of course then we would
have to imagine that the שולחן Shulchan in the תורה Torah in
the מקדש Mikdash has a plating on it, I guess it's the
difference between, you know, has a plating that somehow could easily come
off, which
looks like the ארון הקודש Aron HaKodesh itself? It's three boxes.
Ah, according to that, right. Right. That's some idea like that, although
how you would do that functionally by a שולחן Shulchan I have
no idea. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this. אבל, Aval, הבעי
מיניה ריש לקיש מרבי יוחנן,
Ibaei minei Resh Lakish
mi'Rabbi Yochanan, ריש לקיש Resh Lakish asks רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, בציפוי
עומד או בציפוי שאינו עומד? Betzipui omed o betzipui she'eino omed? Does
this idea that it changes the status apply only when it's a
plating that really stands, or even a plating that could be removed?
בחופה את הלזבז או בשאינו חופה את הלזבז? Bechofeh et halizbez o
beshe'eino chofeh et halizbez? I can't even say that word. לזבז... Lizbez...
לביזבז? Levizbaz? Oh my god, somebody say that word. What? לביזבז? Levizbaz?
I don't know. Anyway, okay, whatever. Anyway, okay, so anyway, or is
it something that even when only when it covers the, sort of
the edge of it, or even when it doesn't cover like the,
you know, the edge of it? How complete does the covering have
to be? ואמר ליה, Ve'amar lei, he said to him, לא שני
בציפוי עומד ולא שני בציפוי שאינו עומד, Lo shani betzipui omed velo
shani betzipui she'eino omed, it doesn't matter if the plating is, sort
of, you know, permanent or can be removed. לא שני בחופה את
הלזבז ולא שני בשאינו חופה את הלזבז, Lo shani bechofeh et halizbez
velo shani beshe'eino chofeh et halizbez, it doesn't matter if it covers
the, sort of edge, the trim, or it doesn't cover the trim,
anyway the coating changes the status. So, back to the point: why
do we have to say that the שולחן Shulchan becomes, can become
טמא tamei because it gets moved? It could become טמא tamei because
it's metal! אלא שאני שולחן דרחמנא קרייה עץ. Ela shani Shulchan de'Rachmana
krayei etz. Ah, the שולחן Shulchan is different because even though it
normally, halachically, top of נט עמוד א, Nun-Tet Amud Aleph, should have
a status of a gold vessel, the תורה Torah calls it a
wooden vessel. That halachically gives it the status of a wooden vessel.
דכתיב המזבח עץ שלוש אמות. Dechtiv hamizbe'ach etz shalosh amot. Now notice
by the way, they say רחמנא Rachmana and the פסוק pasuk is
in יחזקאל. Yechezkel. Okay, the altar, the wood altar, three אמות amot
גבוה, gavoha, וארכו שתי אמות ומקצועותיו לו וארכו וקירותיו עץ. ve'orko shtei
amot umiktzotav lo ve'orko vekirotav etz. Okay, so that's about the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. But then it says, וידבר אלי זה השולחן אשר לפני השם.
Vayedaber elai zeh hashulchan asher lifnei Hashem. So this is the table
before God. Now you might want to be talking about the מזבח
mizbe'ach as if a table because we talk about offering up the
sacrifices on God's table, right? Even when the גמרא Gemara speaks, by
the way, I'll remind you about a גמרא Gemara that spoke about
you bringing an עולה olah to God and you bring a שלמים...
shlamim... שלמי חגיגה shalmei chagigah for yourself, and it says שולחן מלא
ושולחן רבך ריקם, shulchan malei veshulchan rabecha reikam, right, talking about bringing
things on the, on the מזבח mizbe'ach as שולחן רבך, shulchan rabecha,
your Master's table. So anyway, that's simple sense of the פסוק. pasuk.
But the גמרא Gemara says, פתח
במזבח וסיים בשולחן? Patach bemizbe'ach vesiyeim beshulchan? It opens with a מזבח
mizbe'ach and
ends
with
שולחן? shulchan? רבי יוחנן
וריש
לקיש דאמרי
תרווייהו.
Rabbi
Yochanan
ve'Resh
Lakish
de'amri
tarveihu.
So, it's funny, like the, so the answer is essentially, so it's
funny because now it's going to give a דרש, drash, but the
point that it's trying to make is that because it opened with
מזבח mizbe'ach and ends with שולחן, shulchan, you see the שולחן shulchan
itself is considered עץ. etz. The same way it says מזבח עץ,
mizbe'ach etz, the שולחן shulchan is עץ. etz. But then the גמרא
Gemara makes a transition to a דרש drash on this. רבי יוחנן
וריש לקיש דאמרי תרווייהו, Rabbi Yochanan ve'Resh Lakish de'amri tarveihu, בזמן שבית
המקדש קיים מזבח מכפר על אדם. bizman she'Beit HaMikdash kayam mizbe'ach mechaper
al adam. When there was the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash around, the
altar would atone for people. עכשיו שולחנו של אדם מכפר עליו. Achshav
shulchano shel adam mechaper alav. Now a person's table is מכפר mechaper
for him. Now what does this mean? So רש"י Rashi says, בהכנסת
אורחים, behachnasat orchim, inviting guests,
right?
But of course, I'm sure we all had our Jewish mothers told
us don't, don't sit on the table, it's like a מזבח, mizbe'ach,
שולחן shulchan is like a מזבח. mizbe'ach. So it's interesting question, right,
what does that mean? Does it mean inviting guests, or does it
also mean, getting back to a theme that I, right, a video
or a theme that I also brought in earlier in this מסכת,
masechet, about how the idea of the קדושה kedushah that we've been
talking about, right, all these levels of purity and and holiness in
the eating, which created all this sort of stratification within the society
that now that there's no מזבח, mizbe'ach, the way we create קדושה
kedushah in our eating is through making ברכות brachot and through washing
our hands, and that becomes our sort of form of sanctified eating,
you know? So you eat it with the recognition of God and
you eat it, sort of, bringing God into it. So it brings,
so that sort of is, you know, so... so that's like the
transferring of that reality from the מזבח mizbe'ach from the מקדש Mikdash
to our domestic situation, but it's also in a way that doesn't
take... carry with it all of these divisions within the society. So
I think it's worth noting, I don't know if that's necessarily the
פשט pshat there, but I'd like to say it is. But I
think it's worth noting all the ways in which we are, sort
of, countering all the earlier divisions. We had the divisions by עליה
לרגל, aliyah laregel, who's exempt and so on. We had the divisions
that were created by the טומאה tumah and the טהרה taharah and
all those עם הארץ am ha'aretz and חבר chaver concerns. And now
we're getting at the end and what we're sort of saying is,
is that everybody is considered טהור tahor in the רגל, regel, remove
all of those divisions. Everybody, you know, is supposed... when people are
עולי לרגל, olei laregel, the whole idea is that not like before,
oh, only people that we'd want to be in a group, everybody
else like the smelly people are outside, no, everybody is supposed to
be seen as, you know... pulled together as one, everybody is sort
of coming, the access to the מקדש Mikdash is people being brought
in, the מקדש Mikdash is being brought out, and that eventually when
there's no בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash ultimately the מקדש Mikdash is brought
into our homes and all of those, all of these divisions go
away. You don't need special access, it's in everybody's home. It doesn't
create divisions in society. So really is the whole sort of חז"ל
Chazal coming and creating that very sort of populist or
non-hierarchical approach that comes as a contrast to some of those dimension
realities in the מקדש Mikdash very quickly because we only have ten
minutes and we have to finish the מסכת.
Masechet. I'd say from what you're saying the leveling of divisions is
both horizontal in terms of טומאה וטהרה Tumah v'Taharah and vertical. You
become more כהני, Kohani, you become more כהן-like, Kohen you have greater
access to things that only כהנים Kohanim have. It comes into your
house, so it's elevating in a vertical sort of way as well
as those divisions between the people. Right, thank you for that, yes.
So what you're going to say is that we're not טובלing Tovel
all the vessels, we're not saying that whatever was done on them
is like.
Right, it's
exactly the same way like we have to, the food we deal
with after the רגל. Regel.
The משנה Mishnah he was referring to was דתניא חוץ ממזבח הנחשת
ומזבח הזהב וחזקת טומאה ובקודש יקראו ממזבח. detanya chutz m'mizbeach hanechoshet u'mizbeach
hazahav v'chezkat tumah u'va'kodesh yikre'u mi'mizbeach. Right,
so over here we're saying the vessels are טמא, Tamei, but we're
not saying
that, only saying they're טמא Tamei after the מקדש, Mikdash, after the
רגל, Regel, we're not saying they're טמא, Tamei, we're saying just in
case, yes.
They used a פסוק Pasuk from יחזקאל Yechezkel
again and yeah, fine.
Okay, moving on. כל הכלים שהיו במקדש יש להם שניים, Kol hakeilim
shehayu baMikdash yesh lahem shnayim, every vessel had doubles.
מזבח הנחשת, Mizbeach HaNechoshet, except for it said, the altar. So we
were discussing why the שולחן Shulchan could become טמא Tamei and there's
two reasons it shouldn't. It's made for being in its place and
it should be metal, but we said, a, they would move it
and, b, it was defined to be wood. But the two things
that did, were not be able to become טמא Tamei were the
altars because they were connected to the ground. Okay, so let's take
a look.
הן כקרקע hein k'karka is the language of the משנה. Mishnah. So
the גמרא Gemara says מזבח הנחשת דכתיב מזבח אדמה תעשה לי. Mizbeach
HaNechoshet d'ichtiv mizbeach adama ta'aseh li. So it's called אדמה, Adama, so
there even if you would want to call it somehow metal because
it is נחושת nechoshet and etc like we just said before, and
nevertheless it's converted really is like permanently and considered to be attached
to the ground תעשה לי. ta'aseh li. מזבח הזהב דכתיב המנורה והמזבחות.
mizbeach hazahav d'ichtiv hamenora v'hamizbechos. The מנורה Menorah and the מזבחות, mizbechos,
איתקש מזבחות זה לזה. itkesh mizbechos zeh lazeh.
So the מנורה Menorah is able to become טמא, Tamei, but we're
putting that aside, the מזבחות mizbechos are connected. So the מזבח הזהב
Mizbeach HaZahav on the inside is considered, although it is much more
portable, is considered also to be considered part of the ground. וחכמים
אומרים מפני שהן מצופין, vaChachamim omrim mipnei shehein metzupin, and the חכמים
Chachamim say because they're coated. So the גמרא Gemara says אדרבה כיון
דמצופין נינהו מיטמאו. aderaba kivan d'metzupin ninhu mitamu. What do you mean?
We just got through saying that things are coated, they're more able
to become טמא. Tamei. So אימא דחכמים מיטמאים מפני שהן מצופין. eima
d'Chachamim mitamim mipnei shehein metzupin. Okay, so maybe it means they're disagreeing,
they're saying the מזבח Mizbeach itself could be טמא. Tamei. Of course,
one then wonders, then what are you going to do, take the
מזבח Mizbeach and dunk it in the, I don't know exactly what
you would do. Now the מזבח, Mizbeach, I should say the מזבח
הנחושת, Mizbeach HaNechoshet, you didn't have a מזבח הנחושת mizbeach hanechoshet in
the
in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. You had it in the משכן.
Mishkan. I mean there they made it out of basically out of
plaster and whatever, and there it really couldn't become טמא. Tamei. So
then they really were talking because that was really מחובר לקרקע mechubar
l'karka and was all anyway stone or whatnot, but what you're really
talking about is what it was in the time of the משכן.
Mishkan. But theoretically what they would be saying is maybe you'd have
to dunk the מזבח הזהב Mizbeach HaZahav in the מקוה Mikvah afterwards.
So the
גמרא Gemara says ואיבעית אימא רבנן לרבי אליעזר קאמרי. v'iba'is eima Rabbanan
l'Rabbi Eliezer ka'amri. They're saying back to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, מאי
דעתך, mai da'atech, why do you need to quote a פסוק Pasuk
that says that it's called קרקע? karka? משום דמצופין, mishum d'metzupin, because
they're covered and therefore you think, oh they should be metal, but
because I got a פסוק Pasuk I'm going to say that it's
like קרקע. karka. No, מבטל בטיל ציפוייהו גבייהו. mevatel batil tzipuyeihu gabeihu.
Their coating is considered secondary to them and you don't need a
פסוק Pasuk anyway. They would be like we said before, like wood
vessels that are made for being in their place, and therefore it's
a moot point anyway. So one way or the other you'd need,
either it's coated with metal and you need a פסוק Pasuk to
tell you that they're like קרקע, karka, or you don't give weight
to the fact that it's coated with metal, you consider it to
be like a wood vessel and therefore anyway they cannot become טמא.
Tamei. So everyone's agreed they cannot become טמא Tamei then according to
this.
Right,
everyone agrees they do not become טמא. Tamei. Right,
okay, so that, right, fine.
Okay, moving on.
אמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Abahu amar Rabbi Elazar,
תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, now we end with some
אגדתא. Agadata. תלמידי חכמים אין אור של גיהנום שולטת בהן. talmidei chachamim
ein or shel Gehenom sholetes bahen. תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, the fire
of גיהנום Gehenom does not have any, does not have dominion over
them. קל וחומר מסלמנדרא, kal v'chomer misalamandra, a קל וחומר kal v'chomer
from a salamander, which they believed had magical properties that the blood
of it would sort of make you fireproof. ומה סלמנדרא שתולדות אש
היא, u'mah salamandra shetoldos esh hi, the same way a salamander comes
from fire, והסך מדמה אין אור שולטת בו, v'hasach midamah ein or
sholetes bo, and if you coated yourself with it you would be
fireproof, fire would not have dominion over you. תלמיד חכם שכל גופו
אש, talmid chacham shekol gufo esh, תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, that their
whole essence is fire. fire דכתיב הלוא כה דברי כאש נאם ה׳
dechtiv halo ko devarai kaesh neum Hashem so are my words like
fire says God על אחת כמה וכמה al achas kama vechama how
much more so are they protected from גיהנום Gehennom אמר ריש לקיש
אין אור של גיהנום שולטת בפושעי ישראל Amar Reish Lakish ein ur
shel Gehennom sholetes beposhei Yisrael the fire of גיהנום Gehennom has no
dominion over the sinners of Israel קל וחומר kal vachomer
even the sinners וממזבח הזהב umimizbeach hazahav and there is presumably the
link because of the מזבח הזהב mizbeach hazahav or else what did
the other thing have to do with what we were
saying מה מזבח הזהב שאין עליו אלא כעובי דינר זהב mah mizbeach
hazahav sheein alav ela keovi dinar zahav the same way the gold
altar had only a very like the thickness of gold was only
like the thickness of a דינר dinar right whatever that was I
don't know it's like two millimeters let's say
and nevertheless כמה שנים אין האש שולטת בו kama shanim ein haesh
sholetet bo and you know it has the fire on top of
it and nevertheless it now you know the covering never got damaged
so the fire had no dominion over it פושעי ישראל שמלאי מצוות
כרימון poshei Yisrael shemillei mitzvos karimon so the sinners of Israel that
are filled with מצוות mitzvos like a pomegranate even the sinners are
filled with מצוות mitzvos like a pomegranate דכתיב כפלח הרמון רקתך dechtiv
kefelach harimon rakaseich
like like a slice of a pomegranate is your temples אל תקרי
רקתך אלא ריקנים שבך al tikri rakaseich ela rekanim shebach don't read
רקתך rakaseich but ריקנים שבך rekanim shebach even those that appear to
be empty among you there is filled with מצוות mitzvos like the
seeds of a pomegranate so על אחת כמה וכמה al achas kama
vechama how much more so will they be protected from the you
know from the fires of גיהנום Gehennom הדרן עלך חומר בקודש וסליקא
לה מסכת חגיגה Hadran alach chomer bakodesh vesalika la maseches Chagiga and
also וסליקא לה vesalika la you know סדר מועד Seder Moed יישר
כוח shkoiach to everybody and it is very worth noting by the
way that one last point about this is that you know is
that number one the reintroducing right at the very end about תורה
Torah so we were sort of left with you know again sort
of the focus on תורה Torah and מצוות mitzvos as opposed to
all of this which was the focus again on the קרבנות korbanos
which sort of led to these divisions you'll also remember that the
contrast to the עלייה לרגל aliyah leregel or the transition from עלייה
לרגל aliyah leregel was being עולה להקביל פני רבו ברגל oleh lehakbil
penei rabbo baregel if you remember that whole story with the blind
rabbi that they went to visit and the whole fact that the
blindness was an issue by עלייה לרגל aliyah leregel but דווקא davka
then it becomes and it's about תורה Torah and being עולה להקביל
פני רבו oleh lehakbil penei rabbo again something that really gives everybody
equal access so here it ends again with a תורה Torah theme
and with a מצוות mitzvos theme מצוות mitzvos also is universal it's
not about מקדש Mikdash it's anybody has access to מצוות mitzvos and
it really makes the point because it's saying we should treat everybody
similar to the idea that even the עמי הארץ amei haaretz we
treat טהור ברגל tahor baregel right so even the עמי הארץ amei
haaretz we normally say would be טמא tamei everybody even the people
you imagine don't have any מצוות mitzvos right those are the ריקנים
שבך מלאים מצוות כרימון rekanim shebach melaim mitzvos karimon so again this
aspect which is completely democratizing it and really trying to embrace like
all of כל ישראל Klal Yisrael and recognizing that sense of unity
and with that we should God willing go into the next year
and go into סוכות Sukkos
and we should all be able to be רואה בבניין בית המקדש
במהרה בימינו roeh bevinyan Beis Hamikdash bimheira beyameinu